Stock markets function in a very similar way.
股市行为也很相似
When a company first begins trading publicly it typically picks
当企业第一次挂牌交易时
a value for its stock based on certain company metrics like revenue,
通常会根据企业财务数据确定股价
profits, assets et cetera.
例如收入 利润 资产等
But from that point on,
但是之后
it's stock prices almost entirely driven by how much demand exists for its stock.
股价几乎完全由需求确定
But how do you quantify demand?
如何量化需求呢？
Think about it. Demand is nothing but how many people want to own some stock,
思考下需求是指有多少人想要买入某个股票
or how much money they're willing to pay for it.
或他们愿意支付多少钱
In market speak you want to see
用市场行话来说
how many orders people are placing for it and at what price.
需要确定人们以什么价格发出多少个委托
Modern markets keep an electronic record of all orders that have been submitted.
现代市场会保留提交的所有委托的电子记录
People who want to buy a stock can specify how
想要购买股票的人可以指定
much or the limit that they're willing to pay for it.
他们愿意支付多少或支付上限
People who want to sell can specify the least amount.
想要卖出股票的人可以指定最低价格
Again the limit they're willing to sell it for.
即愿意售出的价格下限
Whenever a suitable match is found between a buyer and seller,
买方和卖方被撮合后
a trade is executed.
就会执行交易
It's important to understand how orders are matched.
一定要了解委托是如何撮合的
Let say I submit a limit buy order for two shares of Netflix at $180 each.
假设我提交了 2 股标价 180 美元 Netflix 股票的限价买单
Think of this as an offer or commitment to buy.
可以将这个看做要约或买入承诺
It is also known as placing a bid where $180 is my bid price.
也称为出价 我的出价是 180 美元
This order gets added to the market's queue where
系统会将这个委托添加到市场队列中
all the different buyer orders for Netflix are listed sorted by price.
Netflix 股票的所有不同买方委托会按价格排序
Someone else submits a limit sell order for four shares at $179.90.
另一个人提交了 4 股标价 179.90 美元的限价卖单
This is a commitment to sell.
这称为承诺出售
$179.90 is their asking price.
他们的要价是 179.90 美元
Since that is less than the top most buy order,
由于这个要价低于最顶部的买单
the one with the highest bid price a transaction cannot take place.
即最高的买价 所以交易能进行
If there are enough stocks to fulfill that order then
如果有足够的股票来履行该委托
the next bid could also be fulfilled with that same seller.
那么同一卖方还可以履行下个出价
In this case the top to buy orders are
在此示例中 前两个委托被执行
executed and three out of the four shares offered by the seller are sold.
这个卖方的 4 股卖出中有 3 股成交了
The remaining one share can be used to partially fulfilled my buy order,
剩下的 1 股可以用来部分履行我的买单
and the rest of it can be satisfied by the next seller who offers a suitable price.
剩余部分可以由提供合适价格的下个卖方履行
Say someone else offers to sell three shares at $179.80.
假设另一个人愿意以 179.80 美元每股的价格出售 3 股
This order rises to the top of the sell queue due to its low price.
这个委托因为价格更低 上升到了卖方队列的顶部
Since this is less than my bid price my remaining one share can come from the seller.
由于这个价格低于我的出价 所以可以从这个卖方购入剩下的 1 股
So, in the end,
最后
with my limit order of my two Netflix shares at $180 I got one share at $179.90,
对于我的 2 股 180 美元 Netflix 股票的限价委托 我以 1 股 179.90 美元
and one at $179.80 for an average price of $179.85 per share.
1 股 179.80 美元买入了 平均每股 179.85 美元
This sounds a lot like an auction doesn't it?
听起来很像竞价 对吧
In fact, multiple auctions going on simultaneously orchestrated by
实际上 有很多竞价同时在发生
some authority that ensures every buyer and
并且由某个机构安排 这样可以确保
seller gets the best available price for the stock they want to trade.
每个买方和卖方都能针对他们想要交易的股票获得最佳价格
This authority is the stock exchange.
这种机构称为证券交易所
One problem with this model is that trading can take a lot of effort if
这种模型有一个问题 如果每个人每次想要买入或卖出股票时
everyone has to participate in an auction each time they want to buy or sell a stock.
都要参与竞价 这样会耗费很多精力
What if you wanted to purchase some right away,
如果你想要立即购买呢？
how do you make sure you're getting the best price?
如何确保你能获得最佳价格？
Well, if you're at a farmers' market you might go around asking every vendor,
如果你来到农贸市场 你可能到处问每个供应商
but that's very inefficient.
但是这样效率很低
Fortunately, since stock market transactions are carried
幸运的是 由于股市交易是电子形式
out electronically we have better ways of dealing with this.
所以我们能够更好地处理这种情况
The stock exchange keeps track of the last price at which a stock was traded.
证券交易所会记录股票的上次交易价格
This is publicly posted as the current price of the stock,
并公布为当前股价
and if you wish to buy or sell shares around
如果你想以这个价位买入或卖出股票
that price you should be able to do that immediately.
应该能够立即执行
This is known as placing a market order.
称为按市价下单
But it does introduce one complication,
但是这会带来一个问题
someone has to be willing to sell or buy that stock on the other end at all times.
有人需要始终愿意卖出或买入该股票
That's where a market maker comes into the picture.
这时候就要提到做市商了
A market maker is a financial firm.
做市商是一种金融企业
Usually a brokerage that continuously offers to
通常是一个证券经纪公司
buy and sell stocks at publicly advertised prices.
他们愿意持续以公开价格买入和卖出股票
For example, the New York Stock Exchange has designated market makers such as
例如 纽约证券交易所的指定做市商包括
Citadel securities and J Stryker and Cole who are
Citadel 证券公司等
obligated to make large volumes of shares available for trading.
他们有义务提供大量可供交易的股票
You might think why would someone want to do that?
你可能会觉得 为何有人愿意这么做？
What if a market maker buys a bunch of shares
如果做市商买入大量股票
and then the price starts falling. That's right.
然后价格开始下跌了 怎么办？答对了
They do take a risk by continuously buying and selling.
他们的确冒着持续买入和卖出的风险
But they are usually compensated for that risk by
但是通常可以从这些交易中获得佣金和费用
commissions and fees that they earn on those traits.
从而抵消这种风险
They also maintain a small difference between the bid and ask prices for each stock.
并且每支股票的出价和要价之间都有小小的差异
Say you want to sell some Microsoft shares at market price,
假设你想以市价出售一些微软股票
a market maker is bidding $74 per stock which happens to be the best bid price available.
做市商的出价是每股 74 美元 这是已有的最佳出价了
So the market executes your order with that market maker.
所以交易所对该做市商执行了你的委托
Later, another investor comes in and wants to buy some Microsoft shares at market price.
之后 另一个投资者想要以市价买入一些微软股票
The same market maker maybe asking for a slightly higher price to sell say $74.10.
同一做市商可能提出稍微高的要价 例如 74.1 美元
Assuming that's the best price available they just made $0.10 on each share,
假设这是已有的最佳价格 他们每股只赚了 0.1 美元
that might not seem much.
好像赚得很少
But over the course of a day,
但是在一天当中
a market maker typically trades thousands or millions of shares.
做市商通常会交易数千只或数百万只股票
That easily adds up.
利润就累积起来了
The difference between these prices is known as the Bid-Ask Spread.
这种价格差异称为买卖价差
This is a very important concept to understand in
这是一个很重要的交易概念
trading and comes into play in other situations as well.
在其他情形中也会用到